this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
I almost always begin with the same
sermon about especially when teaching
about quantum mechanics or
relativity the sermon is always the same
it's the fact that we as animals have
inherited through the process of
evolution certain intuitive ways of
thinking about the physical
world uh and if you don't believe it you
think that maybe um ordinary animals are
not physicists you watch a lion chasing
an
antelope and you notice that that lion
the minute at the antelope that the
relative velocity between the antelope
and the lion changes sign the lion just
stops dead somehow he did some
calculation or she it's usually she the
lion did some calculation some Physics
calculation involving some very
complicated concepts of velocity
direction all kinds of uh complicated
computations like
that uh a uh
A Primitive uh chroman man not a chroman
man a
nandal who comes to a cave and sees that
the cave is blocked by a boulder and
tries to push the Boulder and can't push
the boulder decides to aim his body that
way H why so that he gets a bigger
component of force in that direction has
he ever heard of force has he ever heard
of components where did he get this idea
of components did he uh know about signs
and cosiness yes somehow he did know
about signs and cosiness these are
things which were
inherited uh biological in origin and
they are the basis of our intuitions
about physics our intuitive picture of
the
world much of physics has to do with
those things in fact all of modern
physics everything in modern physics has
to do with those things which are Beyond
the intuitions that we were able to get
uh from The Ordinary
World has to do with with ranges of
parameters which are way outside the
range of parameters that humans or
animals ever experienced for example
it's not too surprising that human
beings didn't know how to deal with
velocities approaching the speed of
light that they got the wrong ideas
about how to add velocities when nobody
in 1900 had ever probably had never
probably had never moved faster than 50
or 60 or 100 miles an hour well there
are they probably did when they were
falling off cliffs but they didn't live
to talk about it maybe they got up to
200 miles an hour maybe but nobody ever
had experienced anything like the
velocities approaching the speed of
light and so it was not surprising that
their intuitions that their way of
thinking about adding velocities and so
forth the theory of
relativity was uh and and how you
synchronized clocks all that stuff all
that good stuff that Einstein did that
it was outside the framework of their
ability to think about through
intuitive pictures through intuitive
mathematics um they had to invent new
mathematics the new mathematics was
abstract meaning to say you couldn't
visualize it four dimensional
SpaceTime you can't I can't visualize
four dimensions I've learned tricks to
visualize it so physicists to some
extent rewire themselves or people who
learn physics do a process of rewiring
themselves to some extent to develop
intuitions to be able to deal with these
new ranges of
parameters but still they're foreign
they're alien they're
peculiar even to me quantum mechanics
deals with a range of
phenomena which is also outside the
experience of ordinary humans for which
Evolution simply didn't provide you the
means to visualize Evolution did not
provide you the means to visualize an
electron to visualize the motion of an
electron to visualize the uncertainty
principle when you think of a particle
moving what what is a particle a
particle is a thing with a position at
every instant of time it has a position
if at every instant of time it has a
position it has a
trajectory if it has a trajectory you
can calculate the velocity along that
trajectory just by knowing the
separation between points and what the
time interval is you can calculate the
velocity and that's the
intuitive picture of a particle and
where does it come from it comes from
thinking about rocks throwing rocks
shooting arrows all kinds of things that
human beings normally do so we never
developed the need it would have been
very bizarre if our brains had been
wired to understand the uncertainty
principle why would Darwin have given us
the the uh
incidentally uh if you prefer to think
of uh the intelligent designer go right
ahead I prefer I I prefer to think about
Darwin
but why would either of Darwin's ideas
or the intelligent designer have uh
provided us with the ability to
understand the uncertainty principle
when it's never anything that's part of
our ordinary experience the answer is it
didn't and so Quantum Mechanics for that
reason appears extremely weird to
us physicists as I said rewired
themselves and developed ways of
thinking about it which are intuitive
uh but still quantum mechanics is much
much more unintuitive incidentally than
the special theory of relativity and
what we're going to try to do here is
expose some of the
weirdness of quantum mechanics the
weirdness of the logic of quantum
mechanics the weirdness of how Quantum
information
works this is not a
class a conventional class in quantum
mechanics a conventional class in
quantum mechanics would stress such
things as the schinger equation and
waves and how particles sometimes behave
like waves and so
forth we may or may not get to a bit of
that but that's not the important
subject that we're going to concentrate
on what we're going to concentrate on is
the basic logic of quantum
mechanics the basic logic of quantum
information
Theory physics is
information when you say something about
a physical system you're saying
something some you're giving some
information about it you give the
information in various forms usually in
the form of numbers in classical physics
you often give I will give you some
examples but uh you you usually give it
in the form of real numbers the position
the velocity a set of real
numbers and quantum mechanics
sometimes you use real numbers but very
very
often you give discrete information
discrete information such as yes or no
or up or down or male or
female well that's probably not such a
good
example the differen is between yeah
that's probably I think I'll withdraw
that heads or taals heads or taals do I
have a coin no
uh gonin coin thought coin head tail
head tail right when I flip the
coin head that's a piece of information
it could be tail it's a two valued
system either yes or no up or down heads
or tails or
sometimes they they're logically all the
same of course they're logically all the
same whether we're talking about heads
or taals up or down or whatever it is
they're logically the
same and they're simply decisions which
have two possible or questions which
have two possible
answers and a bit of information which
has two possible answers is called a
bit it's called a
bit and it can either be a classical bit
or a Quantum bit B all real bits in
nature are quantum bits obviously since
nature is made out of quantum mechanics
but sometimes the quantum aspects of it
don't manifest themselves in an ordinary
computer the quantum aspects of the bit
don't really manifest themselves for
reasons that will come
to uh and it's just called a classical
bit classical bit of information this
head the the coin flip uh yes or no the
quantum bit is all is the Quantum analog
of the flipped
coin the yes or no type question but it
is much much more subtle and the first
thing we're going to want to explore is
what is a Quantum
bit now but before we do that let's talk
about classical
bits classical bits can be
described either by writing down a zero
or a one these are we could also use one
and minus one or we could use five and
15 doesn't matter but uh zero and one is
a convenient notation for the two
possible uh values zero could stand for
heads one could stand for tails and so
forth so we're thinking when we're
thinking about this we're thinking about
some physical system when we're thinking
about information we're thinking about a
physical system such as a coin and this
is the information contained in that
coin either a zero or a one uh there's a
notation this seems like a ridiculous
and redundant notation its uh importance
will only become clear when we start to
think about Quantum bits but we're going
to use the direct notation the direct
notation describes the state of a
bit not whether it's californ or Oregon
but the configuration of the bit and
it's usually labeled with a notation
zero
or one or whatever other information
whatever other way you decide to think
about the bit these are the two
states that a bit can have either a zero
or one and it's represented I don't know
if I don't know if I drew that uh well
let's draw it
again
zero or one these are the two states of
a bit all of this extra junk here is
excess you don't need it it doesn't tell
you anything it just says that you're
putting it inside a bracket incidentally
this um pointy bracketed object over
here the thing that contains the
information on the inside is called a
Kat it's called a cat because it's the
second half of something which we will
later learn is a bra
cat or a
bracket there's another
half that we haven't exposed
yet now what about multi-bits supposing
you have more than one bit and we're
talking now classical physics so far
we're not talking about anything quantum
mechanical
supposing we have several coins and I
line them up I label them so we know
which one is which in fact just to in
order to not confuse coins let's make
sure they're different coins Penny
Nickel Dime quarter half dollar silver
dollar okay so we have a bunch of coins
we can't confuse them and we can lay out
some information by saying head tail
tail head head tail that would be some
information about about a collection of
bits right how would you label that well
you would label it with a string of
zeros and
ones so for example uh if we let's take
zero always to stand for head it's easy
to
remember zero stands for
head and one stands for tail for obvious
reasons um right so my string of coins
heads head head head tail head tail head
I would label zero for head zero for
another head one 0 1 one for example
that's that's a configuration of 1 2 3 4
five six coins all right let's say it
was six coins right that's a
configuration of a multi-bit system in
this case six bits
again for reasons that add absolutely
nothing to this description we're going
to stick it inside a
k we stick it inside a k which is just a
kind of notation it's it might be a good
idea to put some commas between these
but maybe not maybe it's just best to
leave it that
way that's a
specification uh it could be the
specification of the bits of information
inside a computer it could be just a
series of heads or tails or so forth but
oh before we do anything else with this
let's ask a very simple
question how many possible
configurations how many possible states
are there of well let's start with one
bit if there's only one bit then there
are only two
states what if there are two
bits well then you can have up up up
down down up down down four 2 * 2 so for
two bits we have 2
squared what if we have a what if we
have 100
bits the answer
is 2 to the 100th power 2 * 2 * 2 * 2
100 * so if you have an inbit system the
number of possible classical fig
configurations is just two to the N
let's write that down let's uh let's put
a notation in let's write the number of
states the number of states N Subs the
number of states of a system of little n
Bits is 2 to the
N let's suppose we oh let's invert that
first of all let's invert little n is
what little n is the number of bits Big
N is the number of
states little n is the number of bits
okay so if the number of bits is four
then the number of states is 2 to the 4
which is 16 and so forth we can invert
this and we can write if we knew the
number of states of a
system then we can take the logarithm of
this
equation log to the base 2 is
particularly convenient if we take the
log to the base 2
of the number of states that's equal to
the number of
bits you can generalize this not every
system has as its number of states to to
a power supposing I have a state a
system um a uh a die you know things you
use in Las Vegas to to throw away your
money with um
it's got
six possibilities one through six that
is not two to the to any particular
power it's just six okay but we can
still generalize this
definition of the number of bits of
information in fact the number of bits
of
information that A system can contain is
by
definition the logarithm to the base
two of the number of states which for
the D would be
log to the base 2 of
six what is log to the base 2 of six is
it an
integer no it's some stupid irrational
number I don't even what is it how big
is it about two to 2 to the 2 to the 2
is 4 2 to the 3 is 8 2 to the 2.5 3 7 9
8 6 14 or whatever so the amount of
information which is always the
logarithm of the number of states does
not have to be an integer but we're
going to be considering systems which
are made up out of some
number of bits Each of which has two
states so for the Simplicity we're going
to be talking about systems the number
of states is always two to a power
that's just uh for Simplicity there's
nothing special about but almost every
system can be represented that way or
approximately represented that way let
me give you an
example uh supposing we have some
question of
physics which has as its answer a real
number but we're only interested in that
real number to a certain
approximation the temperature the
temperature in the room I'm interested
in the temperature in the room to to uh
to a certain number of significant
figures I can represent the temperature
or any other number for that matter by
writing it as a number in base two right
if what's the temperature in this room
incidentally uh it's about
300° um from absolute zero so it's 300 I
can write 300 not as
300 which is what does 300 mean 300 you
know what it means it means 3 * 10 2
plus nothing * 10 1+ 0 * 10 0 but we
write it to things in base two right I
don't know what 300 looks like in base
two somebody can figure it out uh base
two you everybody know how arithmetic
and base two anybody not know arithmetic
and base two okay so everybody knows
arithmetic and base two we write out any
number that we like as a series of zeros
and
ones 1 0 0 1 0
1 0 0 1 that's some number to the
uh uh some particular integer it's an
integer so if I'm interested in the
temperature and I'm not interested in
being uh too careful to Define fractions
I want to know whether it's 72° or 73° I
don't care about 72.
4069 I can write it as an integer and
that
integer can be
represented as a sum of bits not a sum
of bits but as a collection of bits
every number every single
number if you're willing to
truncate the number of decimal
places approximate that number and say
I'm interested in that number only to 35
decimal places or whatever or to 35
places to base two that that number
simply if is both is represented by and
represents a collection of bits so any
and incidentally if you want to have a
finer grain description of the
temperature than than integers in
centigrade you just use a more refined
notion of degree
you go down to ask how many degrees is
it but not in centigrade units but in
units of 10 Theus 100 Centigrade again
you can give it as an
integer and uh integers can always be
represented as sequences of zeros and
ones so almost any information in
physics can be represented in terms of
bits in
particular the measurement of quantity
uh such as temperature for
example let me give you another example
this is a more complicated example of
the same thing supposing I'm interested
in a field a field means a thing which
can vary throughout
space right a thing which can well the
temperature can vary throughout space
the temperature is a field it varies
throughout space it's not one of the
more interesting fields from the point
of view of fundamental of fundamental Al
particle physics or anything but that
certainly is a field it varies from
place to place and how can we represent
that can we represent that in terms of
bits yes if we're willing to tolerate
certain approximations and we're always
willing to tolerate some degree of
approximation what we do is we break up
the
room into a lot of little tiny
cells I won't try to draw a
three-dimensional room in my notes I
drew a three-dimensional room it took me
about a half an hour to put in all the
lines just a two-dimensional
room and here's what we do we first of
all order the
cells we make the cells small
enough so that the temperature doesn't
vary very much from cell to cell so we
might fill this room with several
billion
cells label the cells this is the first
cells 2 1 2 3 4 5 6 I don't know up to a
thand th in 1,00 and 2,3
1004 and we can label all of the cells
and list them once we've listed them we
can write the temperature of the first
cell there's the temperature of the
first C I'm putting a little comma in
just to distinguish between cells then
we can write the temperature in the next
cell 0 0 1 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 I've kept
nine decimal places in in in uh in the
basis in arithmetic and base two uh one
uh one Zer one however till I'm till I'm
finished then I go to the next cell do
the same thing temperature there is 1 1
0 1 0 0 so
forth eventually all I have is a list of
zeros and ones
this long list of zeros and ones if
somebody knows how to use it is
equivalent to knowing the temperature at
every point in the
room okay the same is true of the
electric field the magnetic field
anything which varies from place to
place
so almost everything that I can think of
in physics can be represented in terms
of bits so if you know everything about
how bits work you basically know
everything about how physics works of
course you may not know what the rules
are for for manipulating these things
but uh this is the
basic setup of physics
information in the form of a series of
questions Each of which can be answered
yes or
no now of course you may want to refine
your description to refine your
description you may want to add more
decimal places to the temperature to the
specification of temperature and you
might want
to make your lattice finer that's just
making a better
approximation so the right thing to say
is that most physical systems that we
know about as far as I know all physical
systems uh can be represented at least
approximately and perhaps to always
increasing
approximation by a series of bits that's
why we get to use computers to do
physics if this weren't true we couldn't
use a computer we couldn't use a digital
computer in any case to do physics we'd
have to use analog computers or
something okay so that's uh let me give
you another example another example of
uh how you might uh use bits to
represent another these are all so far
classical systems as I said uh I don't
want to redraw the lattice but I do want
to get rid of this top row here since
I've already mutilated it here's a
lattice uh and what I'm interested in is
the motion of
particles this lattice is just an
artificial imposed lattice that I've
imposed on the room here just so that
I've divided the room into mathematical
cells and what I'm interested in is the
motion of particles moving around in
this room at any given
instant I can ask the question let's
take a very simple case let's take the
case where a particle where you can't
squeeze more than one particle into one
of the cells we can imagine that the
cells are about as big as a particle in
which case you can't squeeze in more
than one then every cell either has a
particle or it doesn't have a
particle we can label the cells that
have particles with an X we can label
the cells that don't have a particle
with nothing or better yet we can label
the cells that have a particle with a
one and the ones that have no particle
with a
zero in that
case this becomes a specification of
where the particles are in the lattice
it's no longer the temperature but the
same long sequence of zeros and ones now
the number of zeros and ones would just
be equal to the number of of number of
cells in the lattice what would this
number mean it would mean that in the
first cell there's a particle in the
second cell there's no particle in the
third cell there's no particle in the
fourth cell there's a particle in the
fifth cell no particle in the sixth cell
particle and so forth and so on and so
given such a string of numbers you are
given a specification of where the
particles are in this
room
um in that way again
motion of particles motion of
fields temperature just about anything
in physics can be represented in terms
of bits any
questions right a bit a bit is by
definition a question about a system
which has only two possible answers
which you can always take to be yes or
no used to be a game 20 Questions didn't
uh uh where uh somebody would think of a
category um uh uh and then you would
stand there and ask uh yes no questions
and until you try to figure out what the
category what the what the category
was uh so that was using the idea of
bits yes question oh I just I just
arbitrarily said supposing we are
interested in the temperature to a
certain degree of
accuracy right so I'm interested in the
temperature to accuracy uh but now I'm
not speaking about temperature I'm just
giving another example these are just
examples intended to show you something
which is which is more or less clear
otherwise we could not use computers to
uh to uh to simulate physical problems
classical physical problem yes right but
you need for for the general real number
you need an infinite number of bits
right any rational number can be
represented by a finite number of bits
and the
rule well that's not quite true you have
to you have to remember to repeat them
but if it's rational it's going to
repeat after yeah if it's rational it's
going to repeat after some point right
so but if it's an irrational number then
you need an infinite string of bits but
in general we will allow infinite
strings of bits uh although not in a
genuine computer well so so far remember
we're doing classical physics all right
so far no quantum mechanics so I will
come let's see where um yes we were
going to come to that very very
shortly uh well let me tell you how very
quickly
uh an
electron first of all we're not talking
about motion yet we're talking about
configuration configuration means the
state of a system at a given instant of
time okay
so uh the presence of an electron at a
given instant of time let's suppose the
nucleus is known to be right over here
and we're not going to ask about the
nucleus the nucleus just sits there it's
a lump on
the all right so um we could say at
instant number one when we begin the
experiment the electron is over here in
that case we would write down a string
of zeros with a one someplace
pure zeros one electron pure zeros
except for one place in the uh in the
sequence where there's a
one okay now if we wanted to describe
the motion of the electron we would say
starting with this
configuration we move and let's use this
symbol here to indicate that at the next
thing we we could we we've broken up
space into a lot of little individual
cells we could also break up time I
thought I had my watch but I don't we
could also break up our watch into a
digital watch which uh which uh
digitizes time just again as either a
convenience or an approximation and we
could say if at digital time number one
the electron was or the or the system
was described by one electron located at
this location then what happens next
next it moves to some new
configuration in this case it might move
over one place 1 2 3 4 five six it moves
over to the sixth place one
two and so forth so the motion of a
system is described by a rule of up
dating of updating information how you
update it from one instant to the next
all right so physics basically consists
of two a physical system consists of two
things it consists of a collection of
possible states which can be labeled by
a collection of
bits and it consists of an time
Evolution which is an updating which
tells you how to take one collection of
bits and replace it by another
collection of bits at a slightly later
instant of time I don't know if that
answers to actually work out uh an
orbital motion orbiting around here gets
confusing because when you jump from one
layer to the next uh if this is one and
this is 100 then 101 is over
here so you don't jump from 100 to 101
you might jump from 100 to over here
which would be 200 so it can be
complicated the updating procedure it
can look complicated but nevertheless
it's an updating procedure that uh that
just updates
your your state of
knowledge uh at each instant of time
that's classical physics now there are
some rules and we're going to come to
them but before we do let's define the
space of State
this is and I want to emphasize we are
still doing classical physics there is
nothing quantum mechanical even though
we're talking about discretizing systems
and making out of them systems of
individual bits so far we are dealing
with what should be called classical
bits C bits I think they're called as
opposed to qits qbit is a Quantum bit
this these are classical bits so far
okay
so let's take all of the configurations
and just abstractly in a purely abstract
way we take all of the configurations
incidentally what are the this about 10
by 10 this is roughly a 10x 10 lattice
10x1 lattice has 100
sites how many states does it have if we
uh I'm not talking about one particle
now I'm talking about any number of
particles can be on this
lattice how many different
configurations are
there two two to the 100 a very very
very big
number 2 to the 100 power that's how
many different ways we can arrange zeros
and ones on this lattice or specify
whether there's particles in in in
various positions a very large number of
possible States but let's just
abstractly think about all these states
and just draw them as points if there
are 10 to the 100 I have to draw 10 to
the 100 points which I'm not about to
do these are the various States these
are not the lattice points these are the
various States for example for one bit
if I had only one bit then the space of
States would consist of only two points
up and down and I would just draw two
points this would be the space of states
of a simple one bit system now let's
ask
uh what are the possible
laws of
updating in other words what are the
laws of motion the laws of motion are
the laws for updating
configurations what are the
possible laws of
of
updating
well here's one possible law of
updating this could stand for heads this
could stand for Tails let's uh let's uh
think about it in terms of coins for the
moment this could stand for heads this
could stand for
Tails right if we start with heads if I
had a coin we would do
it heads and
tails heads
fails all right one possibility is very
simple if you start with heads it stays
heads nothing
happens if you start with tals it stays
tals nothing happens that's a law of
updating it's not a very interesting law
of updating how would you draw that well
here's how we'll draw it
heads goes to heads we'll make an arrow
if we start with heads it stays
heads if we start with T s it stays tals
so we draw an arrow from what you start
with to what you end with what's another
possible law of
updating here's a law of updating if
it's Tails it becomes heads then it
becomes Tails then it becomes heads then
it becomes Tails that's a that's a
little more not very much but a little
more interesting a slightly more
interesting uh system it just flip-flops
back and forth how would we draw that we
would draw that again heads
Tails heads Tails if you start with
heads you go to Tails if you start with
tails you go to heads so the law of
updating in this
case is
um just described by such a diagram
basically a diagram which tells you if
you start at a given State what it will
be in the next instant of time is that
clear right so this is one way of
describing the laws of physics write
down all the states keep in mind what
they stand for of course remember that
in this case one stands for heads one
stands for Tails or whatever it happens
to stand for if it's the male female
this could be an interesting case of uh
this would that would be an interesting
this this would be a very interesting uh
law of motion uh in that case I don't
think I want to I don't think I want to
explore that any further If This Were My
undergraduate class I would never have
brought that
up uh this is more likely this is the
more likely law of updating for uh for
sexuality female
male so you see simple laws sometimes
apply sometimes there a little more
complicated can you think of an
interesting system that flip-flops like
this um off hand I can't think of
anything I mean it's obvious that it
applies to a lot of things but off hand
I can't no no no right right right right
but there yes but if you just you're not
intervening I don't want you to
intervene this is the system by itself
if you had some peculiar light switch by
itself went back and forth and back and
forth and back and forth in a regular
way but that's
uh day and yeah this is
they
which well there's a lot of states to
the pendulum in between but yes you've
got the idea it's it's hard to think of
a simple example uh but I bet by if we
all go home and we came back next week
every one of us would have an example of
a we could call this the flip-flop this
is the flip-flop motion this is the
um uh the uh the UN the UN
motion well we can extend this if we
know what the space of configurations is
and we lay them all
out either abstractly in our mind or
actually just write them on the
Blackboard then the motion of the system
can be represented by a series of
arrows
where
I'm getting tired but
uh and so forth and so
on you only need two
yeah I don't
know
um Let's do let's do the possible let's
think of some possible motions of a two
bit system a two- bit system simply has
four
states that's all we have to know it has
states well here's one possible
motion if we start with this
configuration we move to that
configuration if we start with this
configuration and so forth if we watched
what actually happened with time the
system would move from one configuration
to the next around the closed loop now
the closed loop is not necessarily a
closed loop in space it's a closed loop
in The Logical space of possibilities
here logical space of uh of
configurations that's one possible uh
thing that here's another one perfectly
good
what this is is it's a pair of systems a
pair
of it's a pair of
systems which are separately undergoing
flip-flops each one undergoing
flip-flops this one is flipping and
flopping this one is simultaneously
flipping and flopping if we start over
here let's see what that stands for that
stands for example for both heads could
stand for both heads then we go to both
Tails then we go to both heads then we
go to both Tails or we could start with
one head one
tail and do this that's what this is
this is a pair of systems flipping and
flopping there are other
possibilities
so there are different laws of
motion that the system whatever it
happens to be could have so when you
specify a system you not only have to
specify what the states of the system
are but you'll have to specify how it
moves and how it moves is a rule for
jumping from one configuration to the
next now let me give you an example of a
logically perfectly
sensible
rule but which is defective from the
physics point of view never happens in
physics we can do it I
think well let's do it with four with
with four states with four states let's
see how this uh went yeah here it
is if you start here you go
here if you go here start here you go
here
excuse me one
moment for some odd reason in my notes
I've drawn instead of a diamond shape
I've drawn a square let me go back
there's my four
states okay if you start here you go
here if you start here you go here
if you're over here you go over here and
if you're over here you go over
here all right so now we can say what
happens wherever you start if you start
over here you jump to here you jump to
here you jump to here you jump to here
you jump to here you go here you go here
you go here you go here you go here
notice you never come back to
here okay with this particular
law there's something different about
this
law then there is about the other
examples and all the other
examples well can anybody spot what's
wrong with this well not what's wrong
with it but what's different about
it well it doesn't consist of Loops this
is
true you can't figure out necessarily
where you came from you may be able to
tell where you go next but you can't
always tell where you came from for
example if you find yourself over here
you don't know if you came from here or
whether you came from
here if you're over here you have lost a
piece of
information this is a motion which loses
information it loses information in the
sense that you can't tell where you came
from there's no way to reconstruct the
past but you can reconstruct the future
or construct the future
wherever you are you're told where to go
next but wherever you are you don't know
how to get back if you're over here well
you know you came from here but then you
don't know whether to go back here or to
go back here so this is what is called
an
irreversible
history it's a history or a uh a law
which loses
information and at the fundamental level
of physics fundamental level where
you're really keeping track of
everything not where you're uh not where
you're course graining or not looking
carefully but where you're carefully
looking at every degree of freedom of a
system classical physics never allows
the loss of information like this there
is a
unique Future Point wherever you are and
there is a unique past Point wherever
you are okay that is one of the
laws it's not necessarily a law of
logic it is something which is true of
all physical systems that they are
reversible in that sense yeah let's say
I changed St
twice all right and I'm over
here one two or one two I don't know if
I came from here or
here
right we could give this property a
name we give it the uniqueness of the
Future Point and the uniqueness of the
past point we could invent a name for it
we could call it
unique
tarity do you know what the quantum
version of unique tarity
is it has a
name it's called
unitarity unitarity is a name I just
made up
unitarity is the Quantum
equivalent which tells you that you can
always reconstruct the past from the
future uh the state of a Quantum system
you can either run forward uniquely or
run backward
uniquely and you'll come to some unique
previous state or future
State uh and that's called unitarity in
quantum mechanics well we haven't done
quantum mechanics nothing's quantum
mechanical yet time
symmetry uh it's a kind of time it's a
kind of time reversal symmetry or uh
it's actually not a Time reversal okay
so it's not a Time reversal symmetry
exactly uh it's a time reversibility I
would say this
diagram has a sense of orientation to it
uh if I start some something over here
it goes around this way it definitely
does not go around this way unless I
reverse it unless I look at it backward
in time so it's it's not precisely what
you would call time reversal symmetry
time reversal symmetry means that you
could either go in going into the future
you could go either way but in this case
you only go one way but it's it's it's
the reversibility of the laws that uh
that you can find a reverse law given a
law you can find a reverse law which
will will take you in the backward
Direction I think that's I think that's
right yes yes well two arrows coming
away from a point says I don't know
which way to
go oh boy do I go that way or do I go
that way so it's uh it's it's clear that
that's not a law of motion okay no
branching ratios no branching ratios oh
well let's we do at the moment we're
doing quantum mechanics so I mean
classical mechanics so it gets more
complicated with um branching ratios
and uh let's see classical mechanics is
less fundamental than quantum mechanics
all real systems are quantum mechanical
the question why some of them suppress
the quantum mechanics and you don't see
it is a question which we'll try to
answer as we go along but we might ask
it at the at the quantum level and at
the quantum level I think we can give a
better answer but ultimately at the end
of the day it seems to be a law that uh
that
um B basically says that forward in time
and backward in time are uh are I won't
say equivalent to each other but that
there's no preferred really preferred
sense in which forward in time is
different than backward in time even
though it feels like there is this this
this is this is the question that took
20 years to answer and and
uh uh the answer is in my opinion no it
is not
possible but it was one of the great
questions of uh of physics that uh that
took a long time to answer and I'm not
going to get into it now but it might be
an interesting thing for us to explore
toward the end after we've talked about
quantum mechanics we we have to talk
about quantum mechanics before that uh
makes sense that question y I think
they're all Newtonian in a sense in the
sense Newtonian to me simply means that
there's a definite state for a system
that evolves with time according to a
definite law of uh of deterministic
deterministic that's the that's the
right word yeah but I think you can
think of more complicated situations uh
you just can start drawing some diagrams
yourself and uh and see what makes sense
what the what what reversible what's not
reversible and uh but yes you're right
that is true it loses the information as
to where you came
from the
system after first step yep that's not a
part of the system anymore what do you
mean it's not a part of the system the
system started here it went to here it
went to here it went to
here some later point in time you won't
find that point you won't find that
point ever again right right right but
the main point is you've lost the
distinction between the two possible
starting points whereas in all the other
situations if you know where you are and
you know how many steps you made you can
say where you were well I think uh I
think for a long long time uh Mr Steven
Hawking thought that this is the way
black holes work so not so clear not so
clear um okay no no yeah yeah good good
so let's let's talk about that
um if I take a
uh a bunch of molecules in a bathtub I
what's a good example no let's take the
molecules in this room and I S start
them all out in a certain configuration
very definite configuration I put them
all up in the left-and corner of the
room there and I let him go after a
while the room will be full of air just
like it is if I put him up in that
corner in the room over there and let
him go after a while same thing put it
up in that corner after a a while same
thing so it looks like we've lost
information but in fact that's not true
if we followed every single molecule and
we followed it in infinite detail with
infinite
Precision which we don't do of course uh
then uh then we Could reconstruct by
running everything backward we can
reconstruct the fact that the molecules
may have come from that corner of the
room it's prohibitively
uh impossible to do in practice
but in principle following every single
detail of every molecule now what really
happens in the real world is we lose
information because we lose the ability
to follow the details not because the
information gets lost but because we
lose the because we lose the ability to
follow the information that's where the
second law comes when you start losing
the the ability to distinguish different
states so we don't distinguish whether
uh in our coar grain picture we don't
distinguish the different detail the
level of the molecular detail and so it
looks like different configurations
become the same configuration but that's
only because we simply don't look
carefully enough it's because we're lazy
do you need an infinite number of bits
to ah ah ah you mean in the in a in a
real room like this no because of
quantum
mechanics because of quantum mechanics
no
uh but if it were not for quantum
mechanics yes you would need an infinite
number of bits now what does that mean
that means that you have to specify a
bunch of real
numbers precisely with infinite with
with tremendous Precision you have to
precisely prescribe the locations and
also the velocities but in particular
the locations of every single molecule
with a tremendous amount of precision
and the longer that you want to track
the system the more Precision that you
need so ultimately to track a system for
a long time you need to specify with
infinite Precision the exact positions
of every point every molecule that means
you'll have to give a set of real
numbers a set of real numbers involves
as you say an infinite number of bits so
the answer is for uh for a collection of
real particles moving around that you
really try to follow uh
classically uh depending on how long you
wanted to follow it you would need more
and more bits to describe it oh oh oh
yes yes yes that's right if the room
were really sealed let's let's uh let's
idealize this room so that nothing can
get into or out of the room all
particles bounce off reflect off the
walls of the room so that it's an
entirely sealed up room then the room
can be described discreetly course of
quantum mechanics at least up to some
energy if we know that the energy isn't
uh arbitrarily High then we can describe
it by a uh a discrete collection of uh
of variables that has no exit so let's
say
um yeah so we could so to to make such a
thing we could just reverse all the
arrows here us an
example back to itself no this one has
no exit no just exit to itself well then
if I wanted to exit to itself I have to
do
this we could do that but as I drew it
it had no
exit but but let's let's think about
what it
means let I'm not too interested in what
here the question is what happens when
you're over here all right when you're
over here you have two ways that you
could go and you don't know which way to
go so it's not
deterministic it doesn't know whether to
go this way or this way it might go half
the times this way half the times this
way you might need some statistical rule
50% of the time or 30% of the time goes
this way 30% sorry 70% of the time with
random
statistics that would be
nondeterministic okay so it seems that
the real real laws of nature are both
determin itic forward in time and
backward in time that's the implication
of not having uh Loose Ends floating
around like this that they're
deterministic either way so that
wherever you are you can either Trace
forward uniquely or backward
uniquely and that is all of classical
physics in a
nutshell you have now taken a complete
course in classical physics
all there's nothing that does not fit
that pattern at least to a arbitrarily
High degree of
approximation let's take a uh let's take
a 7 minute
break well I was going to jump to
Quantum Mechanics but before I do um I
want to do a little bit of mathematics
elementary
mathematics most of you know
it but nevertheless let's lay it out
matrices and
vectors
um I'm not at the moment I'm not going
to mathematically Define a vector in any
sort of sensible meth you know even
approximately rigorous way or abstract
way I'm just going to tell you a vector
is a sequence of numbers a finite
sequence of
numbers and you can represent it in a
variety of ways but uh I'll give you two
ways to represent a sequence of numbers
the first way is to write them one after
another let's just give them names uh I
don't want to I don't want to call and
my numbers now I at the moment I mean
real numbers as opposed to complex
numbers I I don't mean zeros and ones I
mean arbitrary sets of uh of uh real
numbers they could be zeros and ones
zeros and ones are fine but they just
general numbers so I just L them what
should we call them
um uh components H components yeah no
yeah they're called components but I
want I want a letter for them a a a is a
is good so
a A1
A2
A3
A4 and just uh put something around them
to uh to surround them so that we know
this would be a four-dimensional vector
right why four dimensional because it
has four components forget don't try to
visualize the vectors now there's no
value at all for our present purposes
and trying to visualize these as
pointing in space or anything like that
they're just list of numbers okay lists
of uh that's one way okay there's
another way that we can list the same
set of
numbers put them in a
column A1 A2 A3
A4 same information in them I mean and
I'm not talking about information in the
abstract sense that I Ed before same
thing sometimes it's useful to write it
this way sometimes it's useful to write
it that way you'll find out as we move
along when it's written in this form
it's called a row Vector when it's
written in this form it's called a
column Vector what we're actually
talking about now is notations neat
notations for uh for doing certain
arithmetical operations involving
collections of numbers isn't one of
those dagger when we get the complex
numbers we will then use complex
conjugate notation yes but for the
moment let them just be real
numbers okay now there's another concept
now called a matrix and you think of a
matrix as the following way a matrix is
a thing which acts on a vector to give
another Vector all right so it's a kind
of machine you put the vector into the
machine and out pops another Vector
according to a particular rule oh no
sorry before we do that before we do
that let's imagine a particular column
vector and another different row Vector
different row Vector has different
entries not the same set of numerical
entries but a different set of numerical
ENT entry so let's call them B
B1
B2
B3
B4 these could be 6.01
5.97
3.04 and A1 could be 7.8 A2 they none of
them they could be the same or they
might not be the same the A's and the
B's this is some particular row vector
and some particular column Vector
there's a notion of multiplying a row
vector by a column vector and the notion
of multiplying a row vector by a column
Vector is a simple is a following simple
operation you take the first entry oh
incidentally the dimensionality of the
row vector and the dimensionality of the
column Vector should be the same that
means that they should have the same
number of entries not necessarily four
could be five six
seven uh in which case they would be
five-dimensional Vector spaces
six-dimensional Vector spaces this
extends to any number of uh entries into
the columns and rows but the rows and
the columns should have the same number
of
entries all right there's the notion of
the product of a row vector and a column
Vector it's called the inner
product and it's very simply constructed
you take the first entry of the row and
multiply it by the first entry of the
column you add to that the second entry
times the second entry plus the third
entry times the third entry plus the
fourth entry times the fourth entry so
the product of these two which you could
could just write as B next to a that
product the inner product is B1 A1 Plus
B2 A2 plus B3
A3 plus
B4
A4 it's a number it's not itself the
product of these two vectors the inner
product is not another
Vector it's not a matrix it is just a
number the numerical value is just
gotten by adding up the column the the
sorry the row times the column in just
this form B1 A1 Plus B2 A2 plus B3 A3
plus B4 A4 is that
clear don't ask me why that's definition
is this what you call the
yeah yeah if we were talking about
ordinary vectors in space it would be
the dotproduct yeah
yeah more abstractly for abstract Vector
spaces it's called the inner
product uh but yes it is the same as the
dotproduct of three-dimensional ordinary
vectors in space where these would be
the components of the vector
yeah okay now there's the concept of a
matrix and a matrix as I
said is an it's an operation that you
can do on a vector
to give a new
Vector right but it's not any old
operation they particular family of
operations that are characterized by
matrices a matrix is
represented by a square
array of numbers let's call the entries
M all right so in the first place we put
M11 to indicate that it's in the first
row and the first column
then
M12 then
M13 then
M14 okay
M what should I call this one to one
it's in the second row but the First
Column this is in the second row second
column second row third
column next one
M31
M32
m33
m34 and
m41
m42
m43
m44 now as I
said uh I've chosen four dimensions just
arbitrarily four is about as many as as
big as I want to handle on the back
board and it's big enough to be a little
abstract so that uh uh it's it's General
enough to see what's going
on all right that's what a matrix is
that's all it is now you can think of it
you can think of it you can think of
each column as a column Vector whose
components are labeled by the first
entry
here okay each one of these can be
thought of as a column Vector where the
first entry labels the column uh uh
entry or you can think of it as a
collection of row vectors where it's the
second entry which labels the uh the
component either way you can think of it
both ways at the same time a a
collection of column vectors or a
collection of row
vectors but all together it forms a
matrix now matrices can mult multiply
vectors so let's put a vector over here
A1
A2 I should line them up more
carefully A1
A2
A3
A4 and when you I don't know I've done a
reasonable job of keeping rows and
columns uh underneath and next to each
other uh but if you like draw some
imaginary lines to separate them into
rows and
columns all right this Matrix acts on
this Vector to give a new
Vector what is the new vector and here's
the rule I've made the vector wide
because each entry is going to be a
fairly complicated expression but it is
just another Vector it's another single
it's another column it's a column which
I've had to draw wide in order to be
able to fit in everything I want to
write down here here's what you do if
you want to find the first
entry into this
column sorry into this row into this row
you take the first row and you multiply
it by the
column the inner product of the first
row with a column here so what is that
that's M11 * A1 + M12 * A2 + M13 * a 3 +
M14 * A4 in other words you take all of
this and you multiply it by this
according to the inner product rule and
that gives you the
first
row M11 A1 Plus M12 a2+
M13
A3 plus
M14
A4 now you want the second
entry into this new Vector over here
done exactly the same way except you go
to the second row and you take the
second row and multiply it by the column
that's going to give you m I'm only
going to do two of these the rest you
can do yourself
M21 M21 again times
A1 Plus
M22 *
A2 plus M2
A3 +
M24 *
A4 and the other two entries you can
figure out you get them by multiplying
the next row by the column and finally
the third row by the column that gives
you a new
Vector it's a way of processing a
vector to produce a new Vector I will
give you some examples
uh as we go
along it's a rule of
multiplication which is very useful the
reason it's defined is because it's
useful and we're going to see how it's
useful by using
it
uh let me give you an
example of how a
matrix
how
the
idea of a
matrix can represent the time
evolution of the
configuration of a system supposing
again we have a our um our configuration
space let's label let's label them let's
take a let's label them the first
configuration the second configuration
the third configuration the fourth and
the fifth configuration these are not
points of space these are configurations
of a system which has five distinct
States and let's take a very very simple
law of evolution the first one if you
start here you go to here if you got
here you go to here if you start here
you go to here if you come here you go
here and what do I do if from
here go to itself go back not well no no
that one that's no good that's that's
disallowed I
think is that disallowed uh I think
that's
disallowed
uh I think that's disallowed yeah that's
because if you find your yeah that
doesn't that's not reversible that's not
reversible that's not what I wanted to
hear what I wanted to hear is that you
go back to
here okay so this is just a um one goes
to two two goes to three three goes to
four four goes to five five goes back to
one it's a
cycle okay here's another way to
represent the same
thing we can represent the state of the
system by a column
vector and the column Vector we simply
insert a one
someplace if I want to represent the
first state over here I put a one and
then a bunch of
zeros one two 3 4 five 1 two 3 4 5 this
simply
represents the first
state what about the second state the
second state I'll represent by 0 1 0 0 0
the third state by 0 one and so forth so
the states of a system can be
represented by a column but a particular
kind of column a column with all zeros
and a one
someplace where is the one namely
whichever State you're focusing on if
you're focusing on the fifth state put
the one in the fifth entry here okay now
what is this rule of evolution the rule
of evolution says that if you have a one
someplace then in the next instant of
time the one moves down
so if you start here the one moves down
to here and the next instant it moves
down to here next instant it moves down
to here next instant moves down to here
then where does it go to up to the top
all right so there's a procedure that
you do on this column to tell you where
the system goes in the next instant of
time that process can be represented by
a matrix so let me let me show you the
Matrix that represents that the Matrix
is an operation on a vector which you
can think of in this case as the
updating operation the operation which
updates the vector so here it
is let's see we put
zero 1 0 0 this is five dimensional so I
need five 0 0 1 0 0
0 0 0 1
0 0
0 I'm sorry I'm going to make this four
dimensional I'm getting sick of I don't
like five Dimensions five is too many
for
me
right one Z
z0 let's try it out let's try it out on
this Vector right over over here this
represents the third state what happens
if we act with this Matrix on the third
state let's just try it
out let's see what we
get well the first entry up on the top
is gotten by taking the top vector and
multiplying by the column 0 * 0 + 1 * 0
+ 0 * 1 + 0 * 0 what's the answer
0 next place 0 * 0 0 * 0 1
time one whoops whoops
whoops I did
okay all
right instead of going down it's going
to go up
but it's okay up and down we just turn
the whole thing over uh would you prefer
let's let's let's just uh let's let's
get it right let's get it right
zero z
z zero where did I have it before I over
here yeah
one
one is then up here one
okay so let's start over again what's up
on the top 0 * 0 0 * 0 0 * 1 1 * 0 we're
still okay zero next one 1 * 0 0 * 0 0 *
1 0 * 0 still
zero what about the third place oh
please please please
God 0 * 0 1 * 0 0 * 1 0 * 0 it's still
0 but now in the last place I have 0 * 0
0 * 0 1 * 1 and 0 * 0 so
one the column has moved down one step
now you can check for yourself here's
your homework
check that any place that you put this
one it will move down by one step till
it gets to the bottom and then it'll
recycle and go up to the
top okay so that's a little thing to
check in fact you can put in any numbers
here uh only zeros and ones may make
sense but we could put in any number uh
A B C D and what will come out over here
here is everybody will move down a step
a b c but then D will move up to the top
so if you put a one in any one of the
places it will slide down one unit and
then reappear at the top the point
is that the evolution of systems can be
represented by
matrices matrices of a particular kind
bunch of In classical physics in this
kind of classical physics there are
always just ones here quantum mechanics
is more complicated more difficult but
in classical physics sprinklings of
zeros and ones so as
to make
the each state shift into the next one
okay that's uh that's an example of the
use of
matrices in classical physics so far no
quantum mechanics just pure classical
physics
um there is a there is an interesting
well all right this this will do for the
time being we'll come we'll come back to
it so
that's an example of Matrix
algebra matrices multiplying vectors
what about matrices multiplying
matrices here why might we want to
multiply matrices by matrices well
here's the idea supposing we wanted to
upgrade or update a second
time to update a second time what we
would do would be to apply the same
Matrix to the resultant that we got in
other words let's write it this way
let's write it
abstractly we have a matrix M which we
multiply by a vector v to get get a new
vector v
Prime okay that's just abstract notation
for writing a matrix and a vector and
getting a new
Vector that's updating the vector v to a
new Vector let's update it again let's
go one more interval of Time how do we
do that well what we do is we write M *
V Prime equals vble
Prime we would do the same up updating
trick except now update V Prime instead
of v and we would get V Prime V Prime
being the state of the system after two
units of time but we could also write
that by realizing that V Prime is M * V
we could write this as M * m * V is
equal to VP Prime this just means we
apply the Matrix
twice we can also think of it
as squaring The Matrix M and then
multiplying it by V so how do you square
a matrix or how do you multiply one
matrix by another Matrix this is what
you would do if you would want to update
twice once with one Matrix and then once
with another
Matrix or the same Matrix how do you
multiply matrices and the answer is
basically the same kind of rule I will
do it now for 2x two matrices because
it's getting too complicated even for
4x4 matrices for a 2x2 matrix we have
M11 M12
M21
M22 let's call it some other Matrix n
n11
n12
n21
n22 the result of multiplying a matrix
by a matrix is another
matrix it's another Matrix
and we do it in a very similar
manner supposing we want the one one
entry here we get the one one entry by
taking the first row and multiplying it
by the First
Column M11 * n11 + M12 *
n21 same kind of in a product and we put
it over
here now supposing we want the next
entry for the next entry we take the
first row because after all we're
interested in the first row up here we
take the first row but multiply it by
the second column over
here so what would be over here would be
M11 * n12 plus M12 * n22 I'm not going
to write it all
out now we can move down to the bottom
to the
bottom if we wanted this entry we would
take the bottom
row and multiply it by the First
Column if we want the last entry over
here we would take the bottom row and
multiply it by the last
column so we multiply matrices by the
same kind of pattern that we multiplied
matrices times vectors we can simply
think of it as multiplying this matrix
by this Vector putting it over here
multiply this matrix by this Vector put
it over here okay so there's a notion of
multiplying
matrices and what multiplying matrices
does is it gives you a new Matrix which
updates you not by one interval of time
but updates You by two intervals of time
if you wanted to Short
Circuit uh uh the problem of updating
and you wanted to update the state of a
system five units of time what you would
do is multiply The Matrix together five
times that's you do it in in sequence
first the first times the next and the
result times the next one times the
result times the next one and you can
you can work out what the Matrix is
which would take you from the state of a
system and an instant of time to a state
of the system five instants later so
matrix
multiplication multiplying matrices by
matrices is also an important
concept
okay one last example
of Matrix
algebra involves row
vectors supposing you have a row vector
and you want to multiply it by a
matrix the
rule is you write the row Matrix
first B1 B2
B3
B4 and then you write the
Matrix M11
M12 M13 and so
forth uh
M14 dot dot dot dot dot dot dot dot dot
dot
dot tired of writing
M's well what's the result going to be
the result is going to
be a row
vector and here's the way you get the
entries of the row
Vector the the first entry of the row
Vector you get by taking the original
row vector and multiplying it by the
First Column Vector over
here that
product is the first entry then you take
the original row and multiply it by the
second column that gives you the second
entry then you take the original row and
you multiply it by the third column that
gives you the third entry over here and
so forth you see the pattern it's always
multiplying rows by columns and putting
them putting the result in the right
place in the right row and column in
this case a row Vector times a matrix is
another row Vector a row a matrix times
a column Vector is another here it is a
matrix times a column Vector is another
column
vector
and a matrix times a matrix is another
Matrix um get familiar with that work
out some examples work out some examples
of your own devising just put some
numbers in
multiply row vectors times matrices
matrices times column vectors and
matrices times
matrices and get the experience of
working out how these things work do it
for 2x two for 3x3 matrices
and you'll get familiar with it because
we will use it over and over and over
again in fact that's the primary
mathematical operation of quantum
mechanics is multiplying rows and
columns times matrices if you know how
to do that and you're familiar with it
and you can read off the answers easily
you've got all of the basic mathematics
of quantum mechanics it would help to
have a little bit of uh uh calculus to
go with it but uh the basic new thing is
matrix multiplication and column vectors
and row vectors so please uh practice
with it a little bit I should have made
up some examples for you to do but um
you can make up your own they're very
straightforward okay are uh we're
getting close to 9:00 Are there any
questions next time we're going to start
talking about Q bits Quantum bits and
how Quantum bits are very different than
classical
bits
question yes what's your name my
name Leonard
susin or
susin you uh if you like uh you know
polishing the Apple for the professor
you can call me Leonardo I like that
very
much well you mean say it the other way
what restriction does reversibility
place on him oh yeah yeah yeah that it
have an inverse okay
right yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah but I
mean in a more if I were
uh in a more abstract sense the answer
is that it should have an inverse that
the Matrix should have an inverse the
inverse of course is the thing that
takes you
back not all matrices have
inverses
so
uh and you want you know what an inverse
is yeah okay good and I we'll we'll if
you don't we'll come to it any other
question yes that that is a good
question yeah uh the final exam is
buying me
lunch
right that's a lot of lunches out there
boy every
look nobody asks me about grading the
class nobody I mean a lot of you have
been here before so you know my
policies my policies are you're here to
learn physics there is nobody here who
is uh here for a degree or uh if you are
then I be glad to give you a numerical
grade if you need one in fact if
everybody needs a numerical grade I know
that there's an enormous difference in
in the level of preparation of different
people here uh and to compare to compare
you in an in an exam setting wouldn't
make sense because I do know that
there's an enormous difference I know
that everybody here is here because you
want to be here and you want to learn
physics and not because you have to be
here uh so uh my policy is uh to either
not grade the course at all or if
somebody needs a grade in order for some
particular purpose uh to uh to give a D
minus lowest lowest possible grade
lowest possible passing
grade all right so it is it's I didn't
tell you what it's for yet I gave you
that's right I gave you an example of
how you can use it to implement the idea
of updating a vector from one uh from
one instument to to another it's one
example and but I haven't told you yet
why we're doing this I often spend I
often spend an hour talking about
qualitative aspects of physics in this
case it was how do you abstractly think
about deterministic
physics uh abstractly in terms of bits
and so forth and then spend uh some time
doing some mathematics which really I
won't tell you what it's for until the
next time but I want to make sure since
I'm going to start doing some quantum
mechanics the next time I want to make
make sure that everybody will recognize
the little algebraic little bit of
manipulations that we'll do and have uh
have the uh the mathematics for the next
time so it's really for the next time
that uh that I set this up yeah you
promise to tell us next time
what I think I think you will see I
think it will be clear I think it will
be clear
uh right I think will be clear yes I do
promise to tell you
why
no is that Quantum junkies uh is that
what it's called that that